Guide to the Isidore Sydney Falk Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1922-1980; Series IV; 5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  - Speeches
    - "The Financing of Health Care (The Prospective Role of the States in Health Care)," Governor's Invitational Conference on "The Role and Responsibility of a State in Promoting Good Health for its People," Chicago: correspondence, background material and drafts of text, 1972 February 18-19 (Box 165, Folder 2466)
    - "The Kennedy-Griffiths-Corman Bill," Medical Committee for Human Rights, New Haven Chapter: correspondence, newsclippings, and outline, 1972 February 24 (Box 165, Folder 2467)
    - "Pending National Health Insurance Legislation," Teamsters Joint Council, Harriman (New York): correspondence, background material and outline, 1972 March 12 (Box 165, Folder 2468)
    - "Financing for the Reorganization of Medical Care Services and Their Delivery," Sun Valley Forum on National Health, Idaho: correspondence, drafts of text and reprint, 1972 June 30 (Box 165, Folder 2469)
    - "Medical Care in the USA: 1932-1972....Problems, Proposals and Programs from CCMC to CNHI," American Public Health Association, Atlantic City: correspondence, background material, drafts of text and reprint, 1972 November 14 (Box 166, Folder 2470)
    - "Organization, Need and Service of Health Maintenance Organizations," Veterans Administration, West Haven (Connecticut): correspondence, annotated outline and notes, 1972 November 30 (Box 166, Folder 2471)
    - "National Health Insurance and Import for Psychiatry," Yale University, Psychiatry Advisory Council: background material, notes and outline, 1973 January 5 (Box 166, Folder 2472)
    - "Social Security Against the Risks Arising Out of Ill Health," National Conference of Social Welfare, Atlantic City: text, 1973 May 28 (Box 166, Folder 2473)
    - "Evolution of Public Policy for Health Care," Cornell University: correspondence, background material and annotated outline, 1973 June 19 (Box 166, Folder 2474)
    - "Some Roles of a Research Program in the Design, Development and Prospective Evaluation of a Group Practice Prepayment Plan," American Public Health Association, San Francisco: correspondence and draft of text, 1973 November 7 (Box 166, Folder 2475)
    - "CHCP and HMO's," Kiwanis Club, New Haven: correspondence and annotated outline, 1974 August 28 (Box 166, Folder 2476)
    - "Implications of a National Health Insurance, with Dr. Spiro, Yale University: correspondence and annotated outline, 1974 October 2 (Box 166, Folder 2477)
    - "Evolution of Public Policy for Health Care," Cornell University: text and notes, 1976 June 22 (Box 166, Folder 2478)
    - "National Health Insurance in the USA: Origins and Evolution, and Some Perceptions for the Future," Health Resources Administration, Rockville (Maryland): correspondence, draft and reprint, 1976 December 3 (Box 166, Folder 2479)
    - "The Debate on National Health Insurance: Before the CCMC Study and Since," University of North Carolina: correspondence, outlines and background material, 1977 April 12 (Box 166, Folder 2480)
    - "Medical Care for the American People: Unfinished Agenda," Georgetown University
      - Correspondence and drafts of papers by others, 1977 May 18 (Box 166, Folder 2481)
      - Correspondence, annotated drafts (I.S.F.) and reference material, 1977 May 18 (Box 166, Folder 2482)
    - "The Opportunities for Comprehensive Group Practice Organizations Within National Health Insurance," American Public Health Association, Washington, D.C.: drafts of text and reprint, 1977 November 1 (Box 166, Folder 2483)
    - "Current Proposals in National Health Insurance," University of North Carolina: correspondence and outline, 1978 March 17 (Box 166, Folder 2484)
    - "The Role of Area-Wide Prospective Budgeting in NHI and Implications for Statistical Systems," Technical Consultant Panel on Statistical Systems for HNI, Washington, D.C.: draft of outline, 1978 September 14 (Box 166, Folder 2485)
    - "Assuring Needed Medical Care to All": annotated outline, undated (Box 166, Folder 2486)
    - Annotated outlines, undated (Box 166, Folder 2487)
    - Miscellaneous reference material, undated (Box 166, Folder 2488)
  - Reprints
    - "Essays on Vital Statistics," The Public Health Nurse, 1922 (Box 167, Folder 2489)
    - "The Role of Certain Ions in Bacterial Physiology," Abstracts of Bacteriology, 1923 February (Box 167, Folder 2490)
    - "The Place of Vital Statistics in Public Health Training," American Journal of Public Health, 1924 June (Box 167, Folder 2491)
    - "Some Riddles in Epidemiology," The Scientific Monthly, 1925 April (Box 167, Folder 2492)
    - "The Effect of Hydrogen Ion Concentration on Certain Antigenic Properties of Clostridium Botulinum," with F. Powdermaker, The Journal of Infectious Diseases, 1925 December (Box 167, Folder 2493)
    - "Studies on Respiratory Diseases, XXIII. Electrophoretic Potential and Virulence of Variants of Type I Pneumococci," with M.A. Jacobson and H.A. Gussin, The Journal of Infectious Diseases, 1925 December (Box 167, Folder 2494)
    - "Studies on Respiratory Diseases, XXV. The Influence of Certain Electrolytes and Nonelectrolytes on the Bile Solubility of Pneumococci," with S.Y. Yang, The Journal of Infectious Diseases, 1926 January (Box 167, Folder 2495)
    - "Studies on Respiratory Diseases, XXVI. The Lysis of Pneumococci by Sodium Oleate," with S.Y. Yang, The Journal of Infectious Diseases, 1926 January (Box 167, Folder 2496)
    - "Studies on the Physiological Action of Light, VI. Alterations in Cell Electrophoretic Potential Produced by Direct Irradiation of the Blood in Vivo," with C.I. Reed, The American Journal of Physiology, 1926 February (Box 167, Folder 2497)
    - "The Influence of Hydrogen Ion Concentration upon the Viscosity of Bacterial Suspensions," with R.W. Harrison, Journal of Bacteriology, 1926 August (Box 167, Folder 2498)
    - "The Fatality of Typhoid Fever in Chicago," The Journal of Preventive Medicine, 1926 September (Box 167, Folder 2499)
    - "Some Statistical Relations Between Mortality in Infancy and in the Subsequent Years of Life,'" " The Journal of Preventive Medicine, 1926 November (Box 167, Folder 2500)
    - "Low Temperature, High Barometer and Sudden Death," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1926 December 11 (Box 167, Folder 2501)
    - "Influence of Some Salts Which Change P. D. on the Phagocytosis of Pneumococci," with T. Matsuda, Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1926 (Box 167, Folder 2502)
    - "How Is Your Heart?," with Herman N. Bundesen, Chicago's Health, 1927 January 4 (Box 167, Folder 2503)
    - "Does Infant Welfare Work Operate to Preserve the Unfit?," American Journal of Public Health, 1927 February (Box 167, Folder 2504)
    - "Some Statistical Relations Between Mortality in Infancy and in the Subsequent Years of Life: Second Paper: Containing Answers to Certain Criticism and Considerations of New Data," The Journal of Preventive Medicine, 1927 March (Box 167, Folder 2505)
    - "Studies on Respiratory Diseases, XXIX. The Influence of Anti-Serum and of Animal Passage upon the Virulence and Electrophoresis of Pneumococci," with M.A. Jacobson, Journal of Bacteriology, 1927 March (Box 167, Folder 2506)
    - "Tuberculosis in the City of Chicago," with Herman N. Bundesen and Grace Lucille Robey, Chicago's Health, 1927 June 28 (Box 167, Folder 2507)
    - "Ultraviolet Radiation from Sunlight and Incandescent Lamps: Its Transmission Through Window Glass and Substitutes," with others, The Journal of the American Medical Association, 1927 July 16 (Box 167, Folder 2508)
    - Reviews of Preventive Medicine and An Introduction to the Practice of Preventive Medicine, 1927 July (Box 167, Folder 2509)
    - "The Degeneration of Complement on Storage at Several Temperatures," with John F. Norton and Blake Barfield, The Journal of Infectious Diseases, 1927 July (Box 167, Folder 2510)
    - "Electrical Determination of Virulence on Diphtheria Cultures," with others, American Journal of Public Health, 1927 July (Box 167, Folder 2511)
    - "Investigation of the Cataphoresis of Toxin and Antitoxin in the 'Field and Teague' and in Other Apparatus," with Mary E. Maver, The Journal of Immunology, 1927 October (Box 167, Folder 2512)
    - "Some Experiments on the Antigenic Properties, Filterability, and Microscopy of Vaccine Virus," with L.W. Hunt, The Journal of Immunology, 1927 December (Box 167, Folder 2513)
    - "The Immunization of Rabbits Against Experimental Pneumococcus Infections," with G.W. Stuppy, The Journal of Preventive Medicine, 1928 March (Box 167, Folder 2514)
    - "A Statistical Study of the Mortality from Tuberculosis in the City of Chicago," with Lucille Robey, The Journal of Preventive Medicine, 1928 March (Box 167, Folder 2515)
    - "Electrophoresis of Diphtheria Bacilli, I. Some Relations Between the Virulence, Toxigenicity and Electrophoretic Mobilities of Diphtheria Bacilli," with L.B. Jensen, Journal of Bacteriology, 1928 June (Box 167, Folder 2516)
    - "Electrophoresis of Diphtheria Bacilli, III. The Development of a Simplified Technique for Electrophoretic Measurement of the Virulence of Diphtheria Bacilli," with L.B. Jensen and J.H. Mills, Journal of Bacteriology, 1928 June (Box 167, Folder 2517)
    - "Survey of the Communicable Disease Situation in Chicago," with others, American Journal of Diseases of Children, 1928 June (Box 167, Folder 2518)
    - "The Colloidal Behavior of Bacteria," Chapter 29 in Colloid Chemistry, 1928 (Box 167, Folder 2519)
    - "A Theory of Microbic Virulence," Chapter XLII in The Newer Knowledge of Bacteriology and Immunology, 1928 (Box 167, Folder 2520)
    - "Studies on Respiratory Diseases, XXIV. Some Relations Between Extracts, Filtrates and Virulence of Pneumococci," with Margaret Pittman, Journal of Bacteriology, 1930 May (Box 167, Folder 2521)
    - "The Spectra and Antirachitic Potencies of Various 'Therapeutic' Lamps," with others, The Journal of Preventive Medicine, 1931 May (Box 167, Folder 2522)
    - "Observations on the Metabolism of Sarcina Lutea. I," with R.W. Gerard, 1931 June (Box 167, Folder 2523)
    - "Fundamental Facts on the Costs of Medical Care," The Quarterly Bulletin of the Milbank Memorial Fund, 1933 April (Box 167, Folder 2524)
    - Review of Fertility and Reproduction, 1933 April (Box 167, Folder 2524)
    - "Organized Medical Services at Fort Benning, Georgia," The Military Surgeon, 1933 July (Box 167, Folder 2525)
    - "The Economic Aspects of Medical Services" (a condensation of Chapters 34 and 35 of The Costs of Medical Care ), with others, 1933 (Box 167, Folder 2526)
    - "Changes in Paying for Hospital Care Considered from a General Economic Point of View," Western Hospital Review, 1934 June (Box 167, Folder 2527)
    - "Formulating an American Plan of Health Insurance," The American Labor Legislation Review, 1934 June (Box 167, Folder 2528)
    - "Present Trends in Health Insurance," Public Health Series, Lecture No. 17, Columbia Broadcasting System, 1935 February 11 (Box 167, Folder 2529)
    - "Health, Sickness and Social Security," National Municipal Review, 1936 April (Box 167, Folder 2530)
    - "Cash and Medical Benefits in Health Insurance," American Labor Legislation Review, 1936 June (Box 167, Folder 2531)
    - "Health Insurance and the Doctor: British Physicians Learn to like It," The Forum, 1936 September (Box 167, Folder 2532)
    - "Health Indices: A Study of Objective Indices of Health in Relation to Environment and Sanitation," with K. Stouman, Quarterly Bulletin of the Health Organization, League of Nations, 1936 December (Box 167, Folder 2533)
    - "An International System of Health Indices: A Preliminary Report," with K. Stouman, American Journal of Public Health, 1937 April (Box 167, Folder 2534)
    - "Health Insurance, At Home and Abroad," American Journal of Nursing, 1938 May (Box 167, Folder 2535)
    - "A National Health Program - Report of the Technical Committee on Medical Care," Proceedings of the National Health Conference, Washington, D.C., 1938 July 18-20 (Box 167, Folder 2536)
    - "Roads Ahead in Health Security," Survey Graphic, 1938 July (Box 167, Folder 2537)
    - "Social Security Measures as Factors in Mental Health Programs," Publication No. 9 of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1938 December 29 (Box 167, Folder 2538)
    - "Compulsory Health Insurance," Journal of Association of Medical Students, 1939 May (Box 167, Folder 2538)
    - "The Meaning of Health Insurance," Journal of the American Medical Society, 1939 May (Box 167, Folder 2539)
    - "Social Security Needs for Vital Statistics Records," with Willard C. Smith, American Journal of Public Health, 1939 May (Box 167, Folder 2540)
    - "Some Problems in the Formulation of a Disability Insurance Program," with L.S. Reed and B.S. Sanders, Law and Contemporary Problems, 1939 Autumn (Box 167, Folder 2541)
    - "An Introduction to National Problems in Medical Care," Law and Contemporary Problems, 1939 Autumn (Box 167, Folder 2542)
    - "Permanent Disability Insurance," American Labor Legislation Review, 1940 June (Box 167, Folder 2543)
    - "Medical Services Under Health Insurance Abroad," Social Security Bulletin, 1940 December (Box 167, Folder 2544)
    - "Medical Care in Public Welfare Programs," with Anne E. Geddes, Medical Care, 1941 January (Box 167, Folder 2545)
    - "The Prevalence of Disability in the United States with Special Reference to Disability Insurance," with B.S. Sanders, Social Security Bulletin, 1941 January (Box 167, Folder 2546)
    - "Medical Services under Government Auspices in the United States and Canada," Chapter 1 in Administrative Medicine, 1941 (Box 168, Folder 2547)
    - "Relationships of Proposed Social Security Disability Insurance to Workmen's Compensation Systems," Bulletin No. 46, United States Department of Labor, 1941 (Box 168, Folder 2548)
    - "The New Social Security Program," Proceedings of the Hospital Association of Pennsylvania, 1943 April 15-16 (Box 168, Folder 2549)
    - "Filling the Gaps of Our Social Security System," The Third Freedom: Freedom from Want, 1943 November (Box 168, Folder 2550)
    - "Proposed Extension of the Social-Security Program, with Special Reference to Health and Medical Aspects," New England Journal of Medicine, 1944 March (Box 168, Folder 2551)
    - Need for Medical Care Insurance, Bureau Memorandum No. 57, Social Security Board, Bureau of Research and Statistics, 1944 April (Box 168, Folder 2552)
    - "Preliminary Report on a National Program for Medical Care," American Journal of Public Health, 1944 September (Box 168, Folder 2553)
    - Principles of a Nation-Wide Health Program: Report of the Health Program Conference, with others, Committee on Research in Medical Economics, 1944 November (Box 168, Folder 2554)
    - "Advantages and Disadvantages of Contributory Insurance and General Tax Systems," Report of the Conference on the Problems of Medical Care (Box 168, Folder 2555)
    - "Content and Administration of a Medical Care Program," American Journal of Public Health (Box 168, Folder 2556)
    - "Long-Term Disability Insurance," Proceedings of the American Association of University Teachers of Insurance, 1945 March (Box 168, Folder 2557)
    - Disability Among Gainfully Occupied Persons, with B.S. Sanders and D. Federman, Bureau Memorandum No. 61, Social Security Board, Bureau of Research and Statistics, 1945 June (Box 168, Folder 2558)
    - "Social Security for Farm People," with Wilbur J. Cohen, Journal of Farm Economics, 1946 February (Box 168, Folder 2559)
    - Need for Medical Care Insurance (report to the Committee on Education and Labor relating to the bill (S. 1606) to provide for a national health program), Bureau Memorandum No. 57, Social Security Board, Bureau of Research and Statistics, 1946 March (Box 168, Folder 2560)
    - Medical Care Insurance: A Social Insurance Program for Personal Health Services (report to the Committee on Education and Labor), Social Security Board, Bureau of Research and Statistics, 1946 July 8 (Box 168, Folder 2561)
    - "Role of Governmental Agencies in a National Health Program," Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, 1946 September (Box 168, Folder 2562)
    - "Financial Aspects of Medical Care Insurance," Social Security Bulletin, 1946 December (Box 168, Folder 2563)
    - "A Budget for Medical Care Insurance," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 1947 March (Box 168, Folder 2564)
    - "Reduction of Dependency Through Health Programs," Public Welfare, 1949 May (Box 168, Folder 2565)
    - "Cost Estimates for National Health Insurance, 1948," Social Security Bulletin, 1949 August (Box 168, Folder 2566)
    - "Health Services, Medical Care Insurance, and Social Security," The Annals of the American Academy of Political and. Social Science, 1951 January (Box 168, Folder 2567)
    - "Medical Care Insurance: Lessons from Voluntary and Compulsory Plans," American Journal of Public Health, 1951 May (Box 168, Folder 2568)
    - "The Economic Issues of Compulsory Health Insurance: Comment," The Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1952 November (Box 168, Folder 2569)
    - "Hospitalization Insurance and Hospital Utilization Among Aged Persons: March 1952 Survey," with A.W. Brewster, Social Security Bulletin, 1952 November (Box 168, Folder 2570)
    - "Medical Care in Two Areas of Southeast Asia Malaya and Singapore," American Journal of Public Health, 1958 April (Box 168, Folder 2571)
    - "The Committee on the Costs of Medical Care 25 Years of Progress," American Journal of Public Health, 1958 August (Box 168, Folder 2572)
    - "Coordinated Health Services in the Canal Zone," American Journal of Public Health, 1959 October (Box 168, Folder 2573)
    - "The Steelworkers Survey Their Health Services," American Journal of Public Health, 1961 January (Box 168, Folder 2574)
    - "Group Practice Is Pattern of the Future," Modern Hospital, 1963 September (Box 168, Folder 2575)
    - "Medical Care: Its Social and Organizational Aspects: Labor Unions and Medical Care," New England Journal of Medicine, 1963-1966, undated (Box 168, Folder 2576)
    - "Medical Care and Social Policy," American Journal of Public Health, 1965 April (Box 168, Folder 2577)
    - "The Quality of Medical Care," Journal of Biology and Medicine, 1965 June (Box 168, Folder 2578)
    - "Medicare: Where Do We Go From Here?," The Modern Hospital, 1966 June (Box 168, Folder 2579)
    - "Medical Care in a University Teaching Program for Hospital Administration," Medical Care, 1967 January-February (Box 168, Folder 2580)
    - Review of Henry E. Sigerist: Autobiographical Writings, 1967-1970 (Box 68, Folder 580)
    - "Medical Care: The Current Scene and Prospects for the Future; Proceedings of a Symposium in Honor of I.S. Falk, Ph.D., F.A.P.H.A.," American Journal of Public Health, 1969 January (Box 168, Folder 2581)
    - "Beyond Medicare," American Journal of Public Health, 1969 April (Box 168, Folder 2582)
    - "Preface to the Reprint," Medical Care for the American People, 1970 (Box 168, Folder 2582)
    - "National Health Insurance: A Review of Policies and Proposals," Law and Contemporary Problems, 1970-1971 (Box 169, Folder 2583)
    - "Numbers of Physicians Required for Primary Medical Care," with others, New England Journal of Medicine, 1971-1972 (Box 169, Folder 2584)
    - "Financing Health Care," Inquiry, 1973 March (Box 169, Folder 2585)
    - "Health Policy: Commentary" in The Challenge ofFacts -- Selected Public Health Papers of Edgar Sydenstricker, 1973-1974 (Box 169, Folder 2585)
    - "Financing and Cost Controls in Medical Care" in Medicine in a Changing Society, 1975-1977 (Box 169, Folder 2586)
    - "Proposals for National Health Insurance in the USA: Origins and Evolution, and Some Perceptions for the Future," Milbank Memorial Fund Quarterly, 1977 January-November (Box 169, Folder 2586)
    - "Making a Case for a Health Security Program," Health Care Week, 1977 December (Box 169, Folder 2587)
    - "Trends in Physician Attendances on Patients: a Corollary," Inquiry, 1978 September (Box 169, Folder 2588)
    - "Cost Estimates for the Health Care for All Americans Act" (report of the Committee for National Health Insurance), 1980 June (Box 169, Folder 2588)
  - Other Writings
    - "The Theory of Electrophoresis and the Measurement of Potential Difference": draft fragment, Circa 1920-1923 (Box 169, Folder 2589)
    - Contributions to the Volume Library: correspondence and drafts, 1930-1933 (Box 169, Folder 2590)
    - Contributions to the World Book Encyclopedia, Annual Supplement: correspondence and drafts, 1930-1939 (Box 169, Folder 2591)
    - Contributions to the World Book Encyclopedia: correspondence, drafts and reprints, 1931-1939 (Box 169, Folder 2592)
    - "Health Insurance," Social Work Yearbook: draft and reprint, 1934, 1939 (Box 169, Folder 2593)
    - Security Against Sickness: book, dust jacket and review, 1936 (Box 169, Folder 2594)
    - "Health Studies in the Program of the Social Security Board": text, 1938 October 10 (Box 170, Folder 2595)
    - "The 'What' and 'How' of Voluntary and Compulsory Health Insurance": text, 1938 (Box 170, Folder 2596)
    - "Social Insurance for Disabled. Workers": correspondence and text, 1939 March (Box 170, Folder 2597)
    - Correspondence with the Grolier Society, 1941 (Box 170, Folder 2598)
    - Contributions to the World Book Encyclopedia, Annual Supplement: correspondence and drafts, 1942-1948 (Box 170, Folder 2599)
    - Winslow memorial article: draft.of outline, Circa 1946 (Box 170, Folder 2600)
    - "The Public Health Movement," Book of Science: correspondence and first draft, 1946-1947 (Box 170, Folder 2601)
    - "The Public Health Movement," Book of Science: drafts, 1946-1947 (Box 170, Folder 2602)
    - "Public Health and Vital Statistics," World Book Encyclopedia Annual: correspondence and drafts, 1949-1950 (Box 170, Folder 2603)
    - "Health Insurance," Encyclopedia of Labor: correspondence, background material and draft, 1949-1952 (Box 170, Folder 2604)
    - "Health" articles, World Book Encyclopedia Annual: correspondence and drafts, 1951-1953 (Box 170, Folder 2605)
    - Security Against Sickness: correspondence re: reprinting, 1962-1963, 1971 (Box 170, Folder 2606)
    - Medical Care: correspondence re: organizing the journal, 1962 (Box 170, Folder 2607)
    - Medical Care: correspondence and text of articles, 1963-1965 (Box 170, Folder 2608)
    - Medical Care: correspondence and reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 170, Folder 2609)
    - Medical Care: correspondence and quarterly progress reports, 1968-1969 (Box 170, Folder 2610)
    - Medical Care: correspondence and articles, 1972-1975 (Box 171, Folder 2611)
    - "Kennedy-Corman Legislative Approach to National Health Care," Health Handbook: correspondence, draft and reprint, 1975-1979 (Box 171, Folder 2612)
    - Medical Care: correspondence and articles, 1976-1978 (Box 171, Folder 2613)
- Personal Papers, 1919-1974; Series V; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  PERSONAL PAPERS is subdivided into Correspondence and Other Papers. Both are arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, I.S. and Ruth Falk
    - General correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 172, Folder 2614)
    - General correspondence, 1944-1953 (Box 172, Folder 2615)
    - Business correspondence, 1927-1935, 1937-1957, 1962-1966, undated (Box 172, Folder 2616-2622)
  - Other Papers
    - Military and selective service records, 1919, 1942-1946 (Box 172, Folder 2623)
    - Biographical sketches and grade transcript, 1936-1937, 1966 (Box 172, Folder 2624)
    - Photograph (I.S.F.): 1 view, 8 prints, 1938 October (Box 172, Folder 2625)
    - Photograph .(I.S.F.): 1 print, 1950 April (Box 172, Folder 2625)